<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-08T05:08:52-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Inference with ULFs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/08/inference-with-ulfs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inference with ULFs" /><published>2019-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/08/inference-with-ulfs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/08/inference-with-ulfs/">&lt;!-- %``````````````````````````````` --&gt;

&lt;!-- % I'M CONSIDERING KEEPING (SOME OF) THIS: --&gt;
&lt;!-- % As justified in detail in (Schubert 2000), ULF and EL sharply distinguish  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % propositions from events (more generally episodes). Propositions  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % are abstract, true or false &lt;i&gt;information&lt;/i&gt; objects and as such can  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % be &lt;i&gt;asserted, known, believed, disputed, etc.&lt;/i&gt;; whereas events are  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % surely real, temporal entities in the world, often with causal consequences  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % -/- without them, there would be no natural or social world as we know it.  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % Consider for example,\\[.03in] --&gt;
&lt;!-- % \ind &lt;i&gt;Molly barked last night; &lt;u&gt;that&lt;/u&gt; woke up the neighbors.&lt;/i&gt;\\ --&gt;
&lt;!-- % \ind &lt;i&gt;Molly barked last night; &lt;u&gt;that&lt;/u&gt;'s what the neighbors assert.&lt;/i&gt;\\[.03in] --&gt;
&lt;!-- % Note that propositions don't wake neighbors, but events certainly can; --&gt;
&lt;!-- % and events can't be asserted, but propositions certainly can. Events --&gt;
&lt;!-- % can have temporal parts at any scale, and can physically involve many --&gt;
&lt;!-- % entities, but propositions cannot. Propositions and events are easily  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % confused because they are closely related: NL sentences &lt;i&gt;express&lt;/i&gt;  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % propositions and at the same time &lt;i&gt;characterize&lt;/i&gt; events or situations.  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % But an adequate semantic representation must distinguish them, thus  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % providing distinct referents for the two instances of the anaphoric  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % &lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt; in the above sentences. For a full discussion see (Schubert --&gt;
&lt;!-- % 2000) and also (Zucchi 1989). In general, propositions believed (or rejected) --&gt;
&lt;!-- % by people are central to explaining the &lt;i&gt;reasons&lt;/i&gt; for their actions,  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % while events interact &lt;i&gt;causally&lt;/i&gt;. In EL, the propositional referent  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % in the second sentence is provided simply by applying the sentence reifying  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % operator to the meaning of the sentence. The next paragraph explains how  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % the event (episode) referent in the first sentence is obtained. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An important insight of NLog research is that language can be used
directly for inference, requiring only phrase structure analysis 
and upward/downward entailment marking (polarity) of phrasal contexts. 
This means that NLog inferences are &lt;i&gt;situated&lt;/i&gt; inferences, i.e.,
their meaning is just as dependent on the utterance setting and discourse
state as the linguistic ``input&quot; that drives them.

&lt;p&gt;
This insight carries over to ULFs, and provides a separate justification
for computing ULFs, apart from their utility in the process of deriving
deep, context-independent, canonicalized meaning representations from
language. Our evaluation of the English-to-ULF parser that we are proposing
to develop will be formulated in terms of certain classes of situated
inferences enabled by ULFs. 

&lt;p&gt;
ULFs in principle provide a more reliable and more general basis 
for situated inference than mere phrase structure, because of the coherent 
semantic type structure they encode. Greater reliability also leads to 
the possibility of spontaneous forward inferencing, as opposed to 
inference guided by propositions to be confirmed or disconfirmed (as 
in most textual entailment and NLog studies to date). This is important, 
because human language understanding seems to involve continuous forward 
inferencing. As a simple example, if according to your paper or newsfeed 
&lt;i&gt;&quot;Police reported that the vehicle struck several cars&quot;&lt;/i&gt;, you will 
conclude that the reported event almost certainly happened, and further, 
that the cars involved were all damaged. Now, the first of these inferences 
requires only a small amount of knowledge about communication, to the 
effect that &lt;i&gt;reporting&lt;/i&gt; (in your preferred media) typically involves 
reporting of facts; whereas the latter depends on very specific world 
knowledge. Our demonstration of ULF utility in forward inference will
focus on the former kinds of inference (and related ones), since 
accumulation of sufficient world knowledge for enabling the latter
kinds of inference remains out of reach in the short run.

&lt;p&gt;
Here, briefly, are some kinds of inferences we can expect ULFs to support:
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt; &lt;i&gt;NLog inferences based on generalizations/specializations&lt;/i&gt;.
   For example, &lt;i&gt;&quot;Every NATO member sent troops to Afghanistan&quot;&lt;/i&gt;, 
   together with the knowledge that France is a NATO member and that 
   Afghanistan is a country entails that &lt;i&gt;France sent troops to
   Afghanistan&lt;/i&gt; and that &lt;i&gt;France sent troops to a country&lt;/i&gt;.
   Such inferences are within the scope of NLog-based and ULF-based 
   methods, and can help in finding inference paths to candidate 
   entailments; but they will not be our focus as they rarely seem 
   worthwhile as spontaneous forward inferences from sentences in
   discourse (we are particularly interested in dialogue settings).
 &lt;li&gt; &lt;i&gt;NLog inferences based on implicatives&lt;/i&gt;. For example, &lt;i&gt;&quot;She
   managed to quit smoking&quot;&lt;/i&gt; entails that &lt;i&gt;&quot;She quit smoking&quot;&lt;/i&gt; (and
   the negation of the premise leads to the opposite conclusion). We
   already demonstrated such inferences in our framework for various
   headlines~\cite{stratos2011KEOD}, such as the inference from
   &lt;i&gt;Oprah is shocked that Obama gets no respect&lt;/i&gt; (Fox News 2011) 
   to &lt;i&gt;Obama gets no respect&lt;/i&gt;. Such inferences are surely important
   -- and immediate -- in language understanding, and will be included
   in our evaluations.
 &lt;li&gt; &lt;i&gt;Inferences based on attitudinal and communicative verbs&lt;/i&gt;.
   Some such inferences, for instance for &lt;i&gt;knowing-that&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;
     finding-out-that&lt;/i&gt;, fall under the previous heading, but others do
   not. For example, &lt;i&gt;&quot;John denounced Bill as a charlatan&quot;&lt;/i&gt;
   entails that &lt;i&gt;John probably believes that Bill is a charlatan&lt;/i&gt;,
   that &lt;i&gt;John asserted to his listeners (or readers) that Bill is 
     a charlatan&lt;/i&gt;, and that &lt;i&gt;John wanted his listeners (or readers)
     to believe that Bill is a charlatan&lt;/i&gt;. Such inferences would be hard
   to capture within NLog, since they are partially probabilistic,
   require structural elaboration, and depend on constituent types.
   &lt;!-- % [GK]: My guess is that the readers won't necessarily grasp why this isn't part of NLog anyway. --&gt;
   &lt;!-- %For example, the variant &lt;i&gt;&quot;Mary denounced Bill as well&quot;&lt;/i&gt; might  --&gt;
   &lt;!-- %lead to the inference that &lt;i&gt;Mary believes that Bill is well&lt;/i&gt;, --&gt;
   &lt;!-- %if &lt;i&gt;as well&lt;/i&gt; is not recognized as a verb phrase adverbial. --&gt;
 &lt;li&gt; &lt;i&gt;Inferences based on counterfactuals&lt;/i&gt;. For example, &lt;i&gt;&quot;If
   I were rich, I would pay off your debt&quot;&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;&quot;I wish I were rich&quot;&lt;/i&gt;
   both implicate that &lt;i&gt;the speaker is not rich&lt;/i&gt;. This depends 
   on recognition of the counterfactual form, which is distinguished
   in ULF.
 &lt;li&gt; &lt;i&gt;Inferences from questions and requests&lt;/i&gt;. For example, &lt;i&gt;
   &quot;When are you getting married&quot;&lt;/i&gt; enables the inference that the 
   addressee will get married (in the foreseeable future), and that 
   the questioner wants to know the expected date of the event, and
   expects that the addressee probably knows the answer, and will supply
   it. Similarly an apparent request such as &lt;i&gt;&quot;Could you close the 
     door?&quot;&lt;/i&gt; implies that the speaker wants the addressee to close the 
   door, and expects he or she will do so. There are subtleties in the
   distinction between questions and requests that can be captured 
   in ULF and made use of.
&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;


        &lt;!--
        &lt;div class=&quot;deets&quot;&gt;
          The ULF Project is aimed at learning a parser for primal logical forms of Episodic Logic (EL)~\ref{..} -- called unscoped logical forms (ULF) -- by obtaining a moderately large hand annotated corpus and training on statistical parser with guidance from knowledge about the formal restrictions of ULFs.
        
          
          &lt;p&gt;
          &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        --&gt;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;

&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[&quot;gene&quot;, &quot;len&quot;]</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to ULF Type Structure</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/08/introduction-to-ulf-type-structure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to ULF Type Structure" /><published>2019-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/08/introduction-to-ulf-type-structure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/08/introduction-to-ulf-type-structure/">&lt;!-- %`````````````````````````````` --&gt;

&lt;!-- % \section{Episodic Logic and Unscoped Logical Form} --&gt;
&lt;!-- % %`````````````````````````````````````````````````` --&gt;
&lt;!-- % Episodic Logic (EL) has been under development for many years, --&gt;
&lt;!-- % and its syntactic and semantic features, the reasoning it enables  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % (using the {\sc Epilog} inference engine), and large-scale extraction --&gt;
&lt;!-- % of EL-encoded general factoids from text have been documented in  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % various publications (e.g., Hwang \&amp; Schubert 1993, 2000; Schubert \&amp; --&gt;
&lt;!-- % Hwang 2000; Schubert 2000, 2013; Schubert \&amp; Tong 2013; Van Durme  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % \&amp; Schubert 2008; Morbini \&amp; Schubert 2009, 2013). The greatest --&gt;
&lt;!-- % remaining challenges in broad usage of EL and {\sc Epilog} in --&gt;
&lt;!-- % language understanding, dialogue and commonsense reasoning are --&gt;
&lt;!-- % the creation of a more accurate semantic parser and the acquisition --&gt;
&lt;!-- % of large amounts of lexical and world knowledge. While our existing --&gt;
&lt;!-- % work on knowledge acquisition is state-of-the-art (e.g., Van Durme --&gt;
&lt;!-- % et al.\ 2009, Kim \&amp; Schubert 2016), its accuracy is limited by --&gt;
&lt;!-- % the quality of semantic parsing; this limitation provides part of  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % the impetus for the present proposal. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following six examples provide an idea of the language-like 
syntax of ULFs. The first two are from the Tatoeba database, the next
three are from &lt;em&gt;The Little Prince&lt;/em&gt; (which was used for the first 
AMR-annotated corpus), and the last is from the Web:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ex-sent&quot;&gt;Could you dial for me?&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(((pres could.aux-v) you.pro ((dial.v {ref1}.pro) 
                           (adv-a (for.p me.pro)))) ?)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ex-sent&quot;&gt;If I were you I would be able to succeed.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;((if.ps (I.pro ((cf were.v) (= you.pro))))
 (I.pro ((cf will.aux-s) 
      (be.v (able.a (to succeed.v)))))) 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ex-sent&quot;&gt;He neglected three little bushes&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(he.pro ((past neglect.v) 
      (three.d (little.a (plur bush.n)))))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ex-sent&quot;&gt;Flowers are weak creatures&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;((k (plur flower.n)) ((pres be.v) 
                   (weak.a (plur creature.n))))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ex-sent&quot;&gt;My drawing is not a picture of a hat&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;((my.d drawing.n) ((pres be.v) not.adv-s
                (a.d (picture-of.n (a.d hat.n)))))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ex-sent&quot;&gt;Very few people still debate the fact that the earth is heating up&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(((fquan (very.adv-a few.a)) (plur person.n))
 (still.adv-s (debate.v
    (the.d (n+preds fact.n 
                    (= (that ((the.d |Earth|.n) 
((pres prog) heat_up.v)))))))))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As can be seen, ULF structure quite closely reflects phrase structure; 
and the type tags of atomic constituents, such as &lt;tt&gt;.pro, .v, .p, .a, 
.d, .n,&lt;/tt&gt; etc., are intended to echo the part-of-speech origins of these 
constituents, such as &lt;i&gt;pronoun, verb, preposition, adjective, determiner,
  noun,&lt;/i&gt; etc., respectively. Originally, ULFs contained some (\lambda)-abstracts,
for example to form a conjunctive predicate from postmodified nouns,
but we have introduced syntactic sugar elements that relieve annotators
from coding such abstracts. An example is seen in (6): The &lt;tt&gt;n+preds&lt;/tt&gt;
macro takes a noun and one or more predicates as complements, and these
are expanded into a (\lambda)-abstracted conjunctive predicate in
postprocessing. As a result, ULFs are relatively amenable to human
creation and intuitive interpretation. Moreover, as mentioned in the 
Introduction, the proximity to surface structure enables NLog-like
inference and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But then isn't parsing into ULF just another variant of syntactic
parsing? The essential difference is that the type tags correspond
to broad semantic categories (certain types of model-theoretic 
functions), and as such enable us to ensure that the type structure 
of ULFs -- their operator-operand combinations -- are semantically 
coherent. Richard Montague's profoundly influential work can be 
viewed as demonstrating the crucial importance of paying attention
to the semantic types of words and phrases, and that doing so leads 
to a view of language as very close to logic; as a result it lends
itself to inference, at least to the extent that we can resolve --
or are prepared to tolerate -- various forms of ambiguity, 
context-dependence and indexicality.

&lt;p&gt;
Our semantic types are not as high-order as Montague's, nor as &quot;rigid&quot;
as Montague's, but they suffice for maintaining type coherence. In
particular, quantification is first-order, i.e., it iterates over 
individual entities, not over predicates, etc.\ -- though through
reification of predicate meanings and sentence meanings, we can &quot;talk
about&quot; kinds of things, kinds of actions, propositions, etc., not just
ordinary objects.

&lt;p&gt;
As soon as we take semantic types seriously in ULFs like the above,
we see that certain type-shifting operators are needed to maintain type
coherence. For example, in sentence (1) the phrase &lt;i&gt;for me&lt;/i&gt; is coded
as &lt;tt&gt;(adv-a (for.p me.pro))&lt;/tt&gt;, rather than simply &lt;tt&gt;(for.p me.pro)&lt;/tt&gt;.
That is because it is functioning here as a &lt;i&gt;predicate modifier&lt;/i&gt;,
semantically operating on the verbal predicate &lt;tt&gt;(dial.v {ref1}.pro)&lt;/tt&gt;
(&lt;i&gt;dial a certain thing&lt;/i&gt;). Without the &lt;tt&gt;adv-a&lt;/tt&gt; operator the 
prepositional phrase is just a 1-place predicate. Its use as a predicate 
is apparent in contexts like &lt;i&gt;&quot;This puppy is for me&quot;&lt;/i&gt;. Note that
semantically the 1-place predicate &lt;tt&gt;(for.p me.pro)&lt;/tt&gt; is formed by 
applying the 2-place predicate &lt;tt&gt;for.p&lt;/tt&gt; to the (individual-denoting) 
term &lt;tt&gt;me.pro&lt;/tt&gt;. (Viewing $n$-place predicates as successively applied 
to their arguments, each time reducing the adicity, is in keeping with 
the traditions of Sch\&quot;{o}nfinkel, Church, Curry, Montague, and others -- 
hence &quot;curried&quot; predicates.) If we apply &lt;tt&gt;(for.p me.pro)&lt;/tt&gt; to another 
argument, such as &lt;tt&gt;|Snoopy|&lt;/tt&gt; (the name of a puppy), we obtain a truth 
value. So semantically, &lt;tt&gt;adv-a&lt;/tt&gt; is a &lt;i&gt;type-shifting operator&lt;/i&gt;
of type (&lt;i&gt;predicate&lt;/i&gt; $\rightarrow$ (&lt;i&gt;predicate&lt;/i&gt; $\rightarrow$
&lt;i&gt;predicate&lt;/i&gt;))), where the predicates are 1-place and thus of type 
(&lt;i&gt;entity&lt;/i&gt; $\rightarrow$ &lt;i&gt;truth value&lt;/i&gt;). Of course, the name 
&lt;tt&gt;adv-a&lt;/tt&gt; is intended to suggest &quot;adverbial&quot;, in recognition of the 
grammatical distinction between predicative and adverbial uses of 
prepositional phrases.

&lt;p&gt;
In the preceding discussion we glossed over &lt;i&gt;intensionality&lt;/i&gt;. For example,
(2) is a counterfactual conditional, and the consequent clause &lt;i&gt;&quot;I
  would be able to succeed&quot;&lt;/i&gt; is not evaluated in the actual world, but
in a possible world where the (patently false) antecedent is imagined
to be true. ULF and deeper LFs derived from it are based on a semantics
where sentences are evaluated in &lt;i&gt;possible situations (episodes)&lt;/i&gt;,
whose maxima are possible worlds. Details about syntactic forms and 
semantic types in our approach to LF have been provided in many past 
publications~\cite{hwang1992thesis,hwang1994ICTL,schubert2000book}.

&lt;p&gt;
There is scarcely space to say more about types in ULF here, but we note some 
further type-shifting operators in the examples: '&lt;tt&gt;to&lt;/tt&gt;' (synonym: &lt;tt&gt;ka&lt;/tt&gt;)
in (2) shifts a verbal predicate to a &lt;i&gt;kind (type) of action or attribute&lt;/i&gt;,
which is an abstract individual; '&lt;tt&gt;k&lt;/tt&gt;' in (4) shifts a nominal predicate
to a &lt;i&gt;kind&lt;/i&gt; of thing (so the subject here is the abstract kind,
flowers, whose instances consist of sets of flowers; and `&lt;tt&gt;that&lt;/tt&gt;' in (6)
produces a reified &lt;i&gt;proposition&lt;/i&gt; (again an abstract individual) from
a sentence meaning. Through these type shifts, we are able to maintain a
simple, classical view of predication, while allowing greater expressivity
than the most widely employed logical forms, for example enabling generalized 
quantification (as in (6)), modification, reification, and other forms of 
intensionality.

&lt;p&gt;
The positioning of &lt;tt&gt;(adv-a (for.p me.pro))&lt;/tt&gt; within the verbal predicate
it modifies, rather than in prefix-operator position, already indicates
a certain looseness in the ULF syntax, as opposed to the rigidity of formal
logic. This is unproblematic because we restrict the way operators may
combine with operands so that type consistency is assured  -- and in fact 
in subsequent processing, any &lt;tt&gt;(adv-a (...))&lt;/tt&gt; constituents of a verbal 
predicate are moved so as to immediately precede that predicate. There
are a number of further kinds of looseness in ULFs, but we defer further
discussion to the next subsection.

&lt;p&gt;
Finally we note a general concern that might be raised about ULFs.
Since they largely conform with surface syntax, they are clearly
language-specific. Isn't the point of semantics to get at the
deeper meanings underlying the surface forms or language, and shouldn't
these be somewhat uniform across languages? Our answer is two-fold:
First, from a semantic perspective, the ULFs for different languages
will have certain essential commonalities, namely, means to express
predication, truth-functional and other connectives, generalized
quantifiers, predicate and sentence modification, predicate and 
sentence reification, implicit and explicit reference to events/
situations, comparatives, and a few other devices. Surface order is
less important than these semantic commonalities. Second, we do
think that sentence meanings should be factored into (as far as 
possible) minimal, separately usable, canonical propositions. This 
seems plausible both from speculations in cognitive science about 
&quot;Mentalese&quot;, and from a practical perspective, since canonicalization
ensures that connections between ideas can be quickly recognized and 
used for inference. A glimpse of the canonicalization process was
already seen above for the sentence &lt;i&gt;&quot;The boy wants to go&quot;&lt;/i&gt;.
Of course the meaning of sentences &quot;in the wild&quot; can be much more 
complex and subtle. Our hypothesis is that we can conquer those 
complexities effectively by starting with a type-coherent surface form, 
and systematically deriving canonical forms, bringing to bear many 
different kinds of influential factors. The next subsection elaborates 
on this view.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[&quot;gene&quot;, &quot;len&quot;]</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Role of ULF in Comprehensive Semantic Interpretation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/08/role-of-ulf-in-el-interpretation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Role of ULF in Comprehensive Semantic Interpretation" /><published>2019-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/08/role-of-ulf-in-el-interpretation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/08/role-of-ulf-in-el-interpretation/">&lt;!-- %```````````````````````````````````````````````````````````````` --&gt;
&lt;!-- % Points:  --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   How ULFs encode possible meanings: --&gt;
&lt;!-- %  -  The set of unscoped elements corresponds to a fixed set of possibilities; --&gt;
&lt;!-- %  -  Deindexing of tense, temporal adverbials leads to a fixed set of --&gt;
&lt;!-- %     possible temporal relationships; (Hwang &amp; Schubert 1994) --&gt;
&lt;!-- % --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   Linguistic phrase structure provides important clues to disambiguation --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   of scope, coreference, elided material, presupposed material, temporal --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   relations. By retaining the essential structure of the input, ULFs  --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   support use of these cues (whether by algorithmic or ML methods). --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   E.g.: The possible positions for unscoped pres/past/quantifiers/and/or --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         are unambiguously determined by their context of appearance in --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         ULF (see Schubert &amp; Pelletier 1982). Further, structural properties --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         bias choices of these scopes (order of appearance, modal embedding, --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         relative wide-scoping tendencies) -\- e.g., Hurum; Hafezi-Manshadi --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   E.g.: Intrasentential anaphora resolution is known to be constrained by  --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         C-command relations and reflexive binding constraints; ULF preserves  --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         the relevant information; --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   E.g., E.g., Ellipsis resolution depends on structural context: &quot;She has  --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         as many books as I&quot;. --&gt;
&lt;!-- % --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   Subsequent scoping and deindexing, followed by canonicalization (Skolemization, --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   conjunction splitting, etc.) typically leads to sets of predications not --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   unlike those often posited in approaches that seek to derive canonical --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   LFs directly from surface strings. Perhaps human language understanding also --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   leads to canonical &quot;Mentalese&quot; forms, and perhaps the appeal of semantic --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   representations in terms of &quot;triples&quot; derives from this. But we contend --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   that starting with a surface-oriented representations and working towards --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   a canonical, factored representation offers compelling advantages. --&gt;
&lt;!-- % --&gt;
&lt;!-- % Another point: Retaining some ambiguity in sentence LFs is desirable, even --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   necessary, because complete disambiguation often requires a broader context.  --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   E.g., Resolving indexicality and deixis (I, you, this, here, now, ...) --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         is clearly context dependent; also, --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         whether a pronoun corefers inter- or intrasententially depends --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         on prior sentences. E.g., &quot;The boy thought he was going to die&quot; --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         may well mean the boy thought this about himself, but not if the  --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         preceding sentence is &quot;Billy's dad was badly wounded&quot;. --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   E.g., Word senses depend on broader context. For example &quot;car&quot; can --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         mean automobile throughout one lengthy passage, and railroad car --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         in another (or even &quot;first element&quot; in Lisp documentation). --&gt;
&lt;!-- %   E.g., Some utterances are radically ambiguous without prior context, --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         such as &quot;How about you?&quot;, with prior statements &quot;I'm a sophomore&quot;, --&gt;
&lt;!-- %         or &quot;I like seafood&quot;. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
ULFs are underspecified -- loosely structured and ambiguous -- in 
several ways. But their surface-like form, and the type structure they
encode, make them well-suited to reducing underspecification, both 
using well-established linguistic principles and machine learning (ML)
techniques that exploit the distributional properties of language.
Many examples of how ULFs lead systematically to (alternative)
disambiguated representations can be found in the references cited
at the beginning.  The scope of this proposal is not expected to 
encompass much of this further processing, but we want to reiterate 
some reasons for regarding ULFs as a suitable basis.
&lt;p&gt;
We have developed and applied heuristic algorithms that resolve scope 
ambiguities and make event structure explicit. Though these algorithms 
are not sufficiently reliable, they set a baseline for future work 
on disambiguation aided by ML techniques. The following points address
the utility of ULFs as preliminary structures enabling systematic
reduction of underspecification. 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Word sense disambiguation (WSD):&lt;/b&gt; One obvious form of 
underspecification is word sense ambiguity. But while, 
for example, &lt;tt&gt;(weak.a (plur creature.n))&lt;/tt&gt; in (4) does 
not specify which of the dozen WordNet senses of &lt;i&gt;weak&lt;/i&gt; or 
three senses of &lt;i&gt;creature&lt;/i&gt; is intended here, the type structure
is perfectly clear: A predicate modifier is being applied to a nominal
predicate. Certainly standard statistical WSD techniques~\cite{jurafsky2009book} 
can be applied to ULFs, but this should
not in general be done for isolated sentences, since word senses
tend to be used consistently over longer passages. We should mention
here that adjectives appearing in predicative position (e.g., &lt;i&gt;able&lt;/i&gt; 
in (2)) or in attributive position (e.g., &lt;i&gt;little&lt;/i&gt; in (3)) are
type-distinct, but ULF leaves this distinction to further processing, 
since the semantic type of an adjective is unambiguous from the way 
it appears in ULF.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Predicate adicity:&lt;/b&gt; A slightly subtler issue is the adicity of 
predicates. We do not assume unique adicity of word-derived predicates 
such as &lt;tt&gt;run.v&lt;/tt&gt;, since such predicates can have intransitive, simple 
transitive and other variants (e.g., &lt;i&gt;run quickly&lt;/i&gt; vs. &lt;i&gt;run 
  an experiment&lt;/i&gt;). But adicity of a predicate in ULF is always clear from 
the syntactic context in which it has been placed -- we know that it has 
all its arguments in place, forming a truth-valued formula, when an 
argument (the &quot;subject&quot;) is placed on its left, as in English. 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Scope ambiguity:&lt;/b&gt; While some of the underspecification 
in ULFs is deterministically resolvable, &lt;i&gt;unscoped&lt;/i&gt; 
constituents can generally &quot;float&quot; to more than one possible 
position. The three types of unscoped elements in ULF are 
&lt;i&gt;determiner phrases&lt;/i&gt; derived from noun phrases (such as &lt;i&gt;very 
  few people&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;the Earth&lt;/i&gt; in (6)), the tense operators &lt;tt&gt;pres&lt;/tt&gt; 
and &lt;tt&gt;past&lt;/tt&gt;, and the coordinators &lt;tt&gt;and.cc, or.cc&lt;/tt&gt; and some 
variants of these.  The positions they can &quot;float&quot; to in postprocessing 
are always pre-sentential, and determiner phrases leave behind a variable
that is then bound at the sentential level. This view of scope
ambiguity was first developed in~\cite{schubert1982CL} and
subsequently elaborated in~\cite{hurum1986AI} and reiterated in
various publications by Hwang and Schubert. The accessible positions
are constrained by certain restrictions well-known in linguistics. For 
example, in the sentence &lt;i&gt;&quot;Browder ... claims that every oligarch 
  in Russia was forced to give Putin 50 percent of his wealth&quot;&lt;/i&gt;, there 
is no wide-scope reading of &lt;i&gt;every&lt;/i&gt;, to the effect &lt;i&gt;&quot;For every 
  oligarch in Russia, Browder claims ... etc.&quot;&lt;/i&gt;; the subordinate clause 
is a &quot;scope island&quot; for strong quantifiers like &lt;i&gt;every&lt;/i&gt; (as well 
as for tense). The important point here is that ULF allows exploitation
of such structural constraints, since it still reflects the surface
syntax. Now, firm linguistic constraints still leave open multiple 
scoping possibilities, and many factors influence preferred choices, with
surface form (e.g., surface ordering) playing a prominent role~\cite{manshadi2013ACL}. So again the proximity of ULF to surface syntax 
should be helpful in applying ML techniques to determining preferred
scopings. &lt;!-- % QUICK EXAMPLE OF SCOPING ALGORITHM OUTPUT? --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Anaphora:&lt;/b&gt; Another important aspect of disambiguation is coreference
resolution. Again there are important linguistic constraints (&quot;binding
constraints&quot;) in this task. For example, in &lt;i&gt;&quot;John said that he was
  robbed&quot;, he&lt;/i&gt; can refer to John; but this is not possible in &lt;i&gt;&quot;He
  said that John was robbed&quot;&lt;/i&gt;, because in the latter, &lt;i&gt;he&lt;/i&gt; C-commands
&lt;i&gt;John&lt;/i&gt;, i.e., in the phrase structure of the sentence, it is a sibling
of an ancestor of &lt;i&gt;John&lt;/i&gt;. ULF preserves this structure, allowing use
of such constraints. Preservation of structure also allows application
of ML techniques~\cite{poesio2016book}, but again this should be done
over passages, not individual sentences, since coreference &quot;chains&quot;
can span many sentences.
When coreference relations have been established as far as possible
and operators have been scoped, the resulting LFs are quite
close in form to first-order logic, except for incorporating the
additional expressive devices (generalized quantifiers, modification,
attitudes, etc.) that we have already mentioned and illustrated.
In our writings we call this the &lt;i&gt;indexical logical form&lt;/i&gt;, or
ILF.

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Event/situation structure:&lt;/b&gt; The most important aspect of logical form 
that remains implicit in ILF is event/situation structure. Much of our 
past work has been concerned with the principles of &lt;i&gt;de-indexing&lt;/i&gt;, 
i.e., making events and situations -- &lt;i&gt;episodes&lt;/i&gt; in our terminology -- 
explicit~\cite{hwang1992thesis,hwang1994ICTL,schubert2000book2}. The relationship 
to Davidsonian event semantics and Reichenbachian tense-aspect theory is 
explained in these references. Our compositional approach to tense-aspect 
processing leads to construction of a so-called &lt;i&gt;tense tree&lt;/i&gt;, and yields 
multiple, related reference events for sentences such as &lt;i&gt;&quot;By 8pm  tonight, 
  all the employees will have been working for 15 hours straight&quot;.&lt;/i&gt;
The relevant point here is that the compositional constuction and use of
tense-trees is possible only if the logical form being processed reflects
the original clausal structure -- as ULF and ILF indeed do.

&lt;!-- % Our approach to the semantics of tense, aspect, and temporal adverbials differs  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % from the traditional Davidsonian approach in that it associates episodes  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % not only with atomic predications, but also with negated, quantified,  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % and other complex sentences. For example, in ELF there is an explicit --&gt;
&lt;!-- % referent available for the phrase &lt;i&gt;this situation&lt;/i&gt; in sentence --&gt;
&lt;!-- % pairs such as &lt;i&gt;&quot;No rain fell for two months. &lt;u&gt;This situation&lt;/u&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- % led to crop failures&quot;&lt;/i&gt;, or &lt;i&gt;&quot;Every theater patron was trying to --&gt;
&lt;!-- % exit through the same door. &lt;u&gt;This situation&lt;/u&gt; led to disaster&quot;.&lt;/i&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- % In addition, we regard perfect and progressive aspect, via operators --&gt;
&lt;!-- % &lt;tt&gt;perf} and &lt;tt&gt;prog}, together with the tense operators &lt;tt&gt;pres&lt;/tt&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- % and &lt;tt&gt;past} and modal auxiliary &lt;tt&gt;will.aux-s&lt;/tt&gt;, as contributing  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % to temporal structure compositionally, rather than by enumeration of --&gt;
&lt;!-- % possible tense-aspect combinations. The compositional process is mediated --&gt;
&lt;!-- % by &lt;i&gt;tense trees&lt;/i&gt; systematically determined by ILF structure. The --&gt;
&lt;!-- % process deposits, and makes reference to, episode tokens at tense tree --&gt;
&lt;!-- % nodes, relating the various times/episodes referred to in sentences --&gt;
&lt;!-- % such as &lt;i&gt;By 8pm tonight, all the employees will have been working --&gt;
  &lt;!-- % for 15 hours straight&quot;.&lt;/i&gt; Details are provided in the publications above, --&gt;
&lt;!-- % especially (Hwang \&amp; Schubert 1994).  --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt; Canonicalization:&lt;/b&gt; Finally, canonicalization of ELF into &quot;minimal&quot; 
propositions, with top-level Skolemization (and occasionally 
$\lambda$-conversions), is straightforward. A simple example was seen 
in the Introduction, and some more complex examples are 
shown in prior publications~\cite{schubert2000book,schubert2014SP,schubert2015AAAI}. 

&lt;p&gt;
When episodes have been made explicit (and optionally, canonicalized), 
the result is &lt;i&gt;episodic logical form&lt;/i&gt; (ELF); i.e., we have sentences 
of Episodic Logic, as described in our previously cited publications. 
These can be employed in our {\sc Epilog} inference engine for reasoning 
that combines linguistic semantic content with world knowledge. 
A variety of complex {\sc Epilog} inferences are reported in~\cite{schubert2013LiLT}, 
and \cite{morbini2011chapter} contained examples of self-aware metareasoning. 
Further in the past, {\sc Epilog} reasoned about snippets from the Little Red 
Riding Hood story: &lt;i&gt;If the wolf tries to eat LRRH when there are 
woodcutters nearby, what is likely to happen?&lt;/i&gt;&quot;; answer chain: &lt;i&gt;
The wolf would attack and try to subdue LRRH; this would be noisy; 
the woodcutters would notice, and see that a child is being attacked; 
that is a wicked act, and they would rush to help her, and punish or 
kill the wolf&lt;/i&gt;~\cite{hwang1992thesis,schubert2000book}. However, the 
scale of such world-knowledge-dependent reasoning has been limited
by the difficulty of acquiring large amounts of inference-enabling 
knowledge. (The largest experiments, showing the competitiveness
of {\sc Epilog} against state-of-the art theorem provers were limited
to formulas of first-order logic~\cite{morbini2009LFCR}.) In the
proposed work we therefore focus on inferences that are important but
not heavily dependent on world knowledge.

&lt;!-- % The potential of EL reasoning has been extensively demonstrated, making  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % the prospect of effectively mapping language to EL an attractive one.  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % The most complete [language $\rightarrow$ reasoning] system built so  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % far (2012-14) was a system for interpreting captions of family photos  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % (e.g., &lt;i&gt;Alice, with her two grandmothers at her graduation party&lt;/i&gt;),  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % then aligning the caption-derived knowledge with image-derived data --&gt;
&lt;!-- % about individuals' apparent age, gend, hair color, eye-wear, etc.,  --&gt;
&lt;!-- % merging the knowledge, and then inferentially answering questions --&gt;
&lt;!-- % (&lt;i&gt;Who graduated?&lt;/i&gt;). Unpublished reports (to ONR) on this work --&gt;
&lt;!-- % exist, but further development has been hampered by difficulties in --&gt;
&lt;!-- % obtaining large collections of captioned family photos for scaling up. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thus ULFs comprise a &quot;primal&quot; logical form whose resemblance to phrase
structure and whose constraints on semantic types provide a basis for
the multi-faceted requirements of deriving less ambiguous, nonindexical,
canonical LFs suitable for reasoning. However, as we have pointed out,
ULFs are themselves inference-enabling, and this will be important for
our evaluation plan.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>[&quot;gene&quot;, &quot;len&quot;]</name></author><summary type="html">ULFs are underspecified -- loosely structured and ambiguous -- in several ways. But their surface-like form, and the type structure they encode, make them well-suited to reducing underspecification, both using well-established linguistic principles and machine learning (ML) techniques that exploit the distributional properties of language. Many examples of how ULFs lead systematically to (alternative) disambiguated representations can be found in the references cited at the beginning. The scope of this proposal is not expected to encompass much of this further processing, but we want to reiterate some reasons for regarding ULFs as a suitable basis. We have developed and applied heuristic algorithms that resolve scope ambiguities and make event structure explicit. Though these algorithms are not sufficiently reliable, they set a baseline for future work on disambiguation aided by ML techniques. The following points address the utility of ULFs as preliminary structures enabling systematic reduction of underspecification. Word sense disambiguation (WSD): One obvious form of underspecification is word sense ambiguity. But while, for example, (weak.a (plur creature.n)) in (4) does not specify which of the dozen WordNet senses of weak or three senses of creature is intended here, the type structure is perfectly clear: A predicate modifier is being applied to a nominal predicate. Certainly standard statistical WSD techniques~\cite{jurafsky2009book} can be applied to ULFs, but this should not in general be done for isolated sentences, since word senses tend to be used consistently over longer passages. We should mention here that adjectives appearing in predicative position (e.g., able in (2)) or in attributive position (e.g., little in (3)) are type-distinct, but ULF leaves this distinction to further processing, since the semantic type of an adjective is unambiguous from the way it appears in ULF. Predicate adicity: A slightly subtler issue is the adicity of predicates. We do not assume unique adicity of word-derived predicates such as run.v, since such predicates can have intransitive, simple transitive and other variants (e.g., run quickly vs. run an experiment). But adicity of a predicate in ULF is always clear from the syntactic context in which it has been placed -- we know that it has all its arguments in place, forming a truth-valued formula, when an argument (the &quot;subject&quot;) is placed on its left, as in English. Scope ambiguity: While some of the underspecification in ULFs is deterministically resolvable, unscoped constituents can generally &quot;float&quot; to more than one possible position. The three types of unscoped elements in ULF are determiner phrases derived from noun phrases (such as very few people and the Earth in (6)), the tense operators pres and past, and the coordinators and.cc, or.cc and some variants of these. The positions they can &quot;float&quot; to in postprocessing are always pre-sentential, and determiner phrases leave behind a variable that is then bound at the sentential level. This view of scope ambiguity was first developed in~\cite{schubert1982CL} and subsequently elaborated in~\cite{hurum1986AI} and reiterated in various publications by Hwang and Schubert. The accessible positions are constrained by certain restrictions well-known in linguistics. For example, in the sentence &quot;Browder ... claims that every oligarch in Russia was forced to give Putin 50 percent of his wealth&quot;, there is no wide-scope reading of every, to the effect &quot;For every oligarch in Russia, Browder claims ... etc.&quot;; the subordinate clause is a &quot;scope island&quot; for strong quantifiers like every (as well as for tense). The important point here is that ULF allows exploitation of such structural constraints, since it still reflects the surface syntax. Now, firm linguistic constraints still leave open multiple scoping possibilities, and many factors influence preferred choices, with surface form (e.g., surface ordering) playing a prominent role~\cite{manshadi2013ACL}. So again the proximity of ULF to surface syntax should be helpful in applying ML techniques to determining preferred scopings.</summary></entry></feed>